I truly love Hitagi Senjougahara.
戦場ヶ原ひたぎを愛している
I can say so without shame.
臆面もなくそう言える
However, to think that I would actually feel
about someone else in this manner...
しかしながら
この僕がそんな風に誰かのことを思うことがあるだなんて
...was something that would never
cross my mind a year ago.
一年前にはまったく 思いもよらないことだった
To love someone else...
was something I feared.
誰かを愛することを 僕は恐れていた
Then why was I so cowardly about
loving someone like that?
ではなぜ そんな風に
誰かを愛することに臆病であったかと言えば
That is a simple, straightforward story.
It was just a self-preservation instinct.
これは簡単明瞭な話
自身が可愛かったからだと思われる
I loved who I was,
and I was afraid of losing that.
その可愛い自身を失うことが怖かった
I was scared of changing.
変わるのが怖かった
I was scared of being changed.
変えられるのが怖かった
If I don't abandon the
foundation of narcissism,
土台 自己愛を放棄しなければ
I can't possibly love anyone
other than myself.
自分以外の誰かを愛することなんてできやしない
For this one point, perhaps Hitagi
Senjougahara feels more strongly about it than I do.
この点については むしろ僕よりも戦場ヶ原ひたぎのほうが
強くそう思っているかもしれない
And, I think that's perfectly fine.
そしてそれでいいのだと思う
Her affection is... probably...
彼女の愛情は たぶん
...too heavy a burden to
point just at herself.
己一人に向けるには重過ぎる
It's just about right when
she shares it with me.
僕と分けっこするくらいで丁度いい
After imagining that far, I had a thought.
そうイメージしたところで はたと思う
I truly love Hitagi Senjougahara.
僕は戦場ヶ原ひたぎを愛していて
And I can say so without
shame... but in return,
臆面もなくそう言えて だけどその分
from some point, perhaps I
have lost my narcissism.
いつからか
自己愛を失ってしまったんじゃないのだろうか
Sure enough, am I able to love
myself just like I love her?
果たしてあいつを愛するように
僕は自分を愛せているだろうか?
If that is not the case...
もしもそうでないのなら
I am as good as dead as a human.
僕は人として 死んでいるも同然だろう
Part One
March 13th
We're going on a date.
デートをします
That's not it. That's not how it goes.
違うわね こうじゃないわ
N-Not it?
ち 違うって?
Well, it's been quite a while since the last
time I had a proper appearance like this,
いえ なにせこんなちゃんとした出番が久し振りなものだから
so I've forgotten what
my character is like.
自分のキャラを忘れたわ
Date me.
デートしろ
I-Isn't your character straying
off course, Senjougahara-san?
キャ キャラが迷走していないか 戦場ヶ原さん
明日よ 明日という日を全力で活用して
Tomorrow. Let us use the day called
tomorrow to its full potential,
半年分のデートをするわよ 阿良々木くん
and go on a date worth six
months' time, Araragi-kun.
Do you understand what I am talking about?
私が何を言っているか わかる?
No, unfortunately, not at all...
いや 残念ながら全然...
Recording
Then, I will explain it to you, much
like the supplementary audio channel.
ならば解説してあげるわ 副音声のように
First off, thank you for all
the hard work, Araragi-kun.
まずはお疲れ様でした 阿良々木くん
Araragi
You gave so much effort until today, so
even if it doesn't lead to good results,
今日まであんなに頑張ったんだから
たとえ結果に繋がらなかったとしても
you shouldn't feel ashamed.
恥じることはないわ
You have already completed your mission.
あなたは既にやり遂げたのよ
Can you stop moving along on the
premise that I don't get accepted?
落ちるのが前提みたいな進行はやめてくれないか
That's not kindness, but consolation.
それ 労りじゃなくて慰めだから
Don't set up foreshadowing for consolation.
I haven't said anything yet.
慰めの伏線を張らないで
まだ何も言ってないだろ
It's not over until the results are out.
結果が出るまではまだ終わってないだろう
No, it is already over.
いえ もう終わったのよ
Your battle ended right here.
あなたの戦いは ここまで
And so...
と言うわけで...
I have been voluntarily refraining
from dates for the past
ここ半年ほど自粛(じしゅく)していたデートを
活動再開したいと
six months or so, and want to resume them.
That is what I am desiring, Araragi-kun.
私は所望(しょもう)しているのよ 阿良々木くん
I will use all the points I
have saved up until now.
たまったポイントをすべて使うわ
Strangely enough, tomorrow is
March 14th, White Day.
奇しくも明日は三月十四日 ホワイトデーです
It is an anniversary perfectly
suited for a date.
デートにはうってつけのアニバーサリーです
You just thought how you hated
anniversaries right now, didn't you?
今 アニバーサリーは嫌いだとか思ったでしょう
How did that come across even when I'm silent?
Can telepathy really be this one-sided?
Our graduation ceremony is the day
after tomorrow, Araragi-kun.
私達の卒業式は明後日(あさって)よ 阿良々木くん
Monday,  March 13th
In other words, the way we are now,
つまりこのままだと私達は
we will end our blossoming days in
high school with hardly any dates.
花の高校生活を ほとんどデートをすることなく
終えることになってしまうのよ
Naoetsu High
Isn't that just too sad a thing?
そんなの 悲し過ぎるじゃない
Well, if you put it that way...
まあ そう言われてしまうと...
That's why.
だから
We are going to go on enough
dates for the past six months'
明日一日で 一気にここ半年分のデートをするのよ
阿良々木くん
worth in one fell swoop
tomorrow, Araragi-kun.
In other words, it's the
abridged "digest" version.
いわばダイジェスト版よ
We are going to execute the highlight
reel of our high school life.
私達の高校生活の 総集編を執行するのよ
Highlight reel...?
総集編って...
The main portion doesn't even exist - how are
you going to create a digest version of it?
I've already got the scoop
on you, Araragi-kun.
ネタはあがっているのよ 阿良々木くん
Eh?
Araragi-kun, your body somehow
has recovered, so I hear?
阿良々木くんの肉体 どうやら復調したみたいじゃない
Oh, well...
ああ いや...
So for you, Araragi-kun,
all your pending issues,
つまり阿良々木くんの懸案は
受験のことも肉体のことも 終わったということでしょう?
both the entrance exams and your
physical body, are done, yes?
It means that they have come
to a conclusion, right?
完結した ということでしょう?
Then, there should be no reason why you
should hesitate in going out on a date with me.
ならば私とデートをすることに 躊躇する理由はないはずよ
If there's any time to resolve the status
of lacking dates, that time is now.
絶デート状態を解消するなら今だわ
Status of lacking dates?
絶デート状態って...
And so, you should go on a
date with me, Araragi-kun.
というわけで 私とデートをしなさい 阿良々木くん
I get it, Senjougahara.
わかったぜ 戦場ヶ原
It'll be more of the wrap-up ending
than a highlight reel...
総集編というより 総仕上げだ
Let's use the day tomorrow to its fullest,
and go on six months' worth of dates.
明日という日をフルに使って
半年分のデートをしようじゃないか
Oh, I'm sorry. The full day is a bit much...
あ ごめんなさい フルっていうのはちょっと
I have something I need
to do in the evening.
夜には私 所用があって
Eh?
So, it's more like early in the morning
until late afternoon, or something like that.
なので 朝早くから 夕方までくらいの感じで
It's fine. All plans are already in here.
大丈夫 すべてのプランは もうここにあるわ
I'd be lying if I said that...
...I didn't feel a vague sense of anxiety.
Roger, roger... Araragi, roger that.
了解了解... 阿良々木了解
By the way, what's this that you
need to do in the evening?
ところで 夜にある所用ってなんなんだ?
See, tomorrow is White Day, right?
ほら 明日ってホワイトデーじゃない?
So I'm going out to dinner
with Father in the evening.
だから夜はお父さんと食事に...
Date? Tomorrow?
デート? 明日?
Come on now, you should tell me
these things a bit earlier.
おいおい そういうことはもっと早く言ってくれないと
It's a bit rushed.
急なんだよね
I have my own circumstances, too.
こっちにも都合っていうものがあるんだから
But well, it can't be helped.
でもまあ仕方ない 鬼のお兄ちゃんのためだもの
なんとか時間を作ってみるよ
This is for Devilish Big Brother's
sake. I'll somehow make some time.
Wait, why are you speaking on the
premise that you are tagging along?
いや なんでついてくる前提なんだよ
What kind of position are you taking?
きみは一体どういう立場なんだよ
What is it?
? なんだい?
Devilish Big Brother. Big
Demo-ther for short.
鬼のお兄ちゃん 略して鬼いちゃん
You are staring at my face.
僕の顔をじっと見て
Is there anything stuck (tsuku) on my
face? After all, I'm a Tsukumo-gami.
僕の顔に何かついている? 憑喪神(つくもがみ)だけに
Well, hold on a second.
いや ちょっと...
Ononoki-chan, I have a serious topic
to talk about. You have a moment?
斧乃木ちゃん 真面目な話があるんだけど
いいかな?
I am always serious. I have never had any
conversation that was not serious.
僕はいつだって真面目だよ
真面目な話以外はしたことがない
Being serious (majime) got so bad that they
called me Grapevine Stretch (manji-gatame).
真面目が昂(こう)じて卍固(まんじがた)めと言われているよ
I see.
Come on. You don't feel anything after
hearing tales of Tadatsuru, one of your creators?
いやいや きみの作り手の一人である正弦の話とか聞いて
何か思わないの?
He told me to send you his regards.
よろしく言うよう 言われてるんだけど
Not really. I told you, right?
別になんとも 言ってるでしょ?
Don't ask me to harbor
such humanly emotions.
僕にそんな人間的感情を求めないでよ
Even if he was dead to begin with, even if he's
immortal in some way, even if he's a living doll,
あいつが元から死んでいようと ある意味不死身だろうと
生き人形だろうと
that doesn't change the implications
of what I have done.
それで僕のやったことの意味合いが変わるわけじゃあないよ
Not for the implications
on you, Big Demo-ther.
鬼いちゃんにとっての意味合いはね
However, there are other
important matters for me.
だけども僕にとっての重要な事柄は他にある
I can't keep from speaking about her master, Kagenui-san.
Kiss-shot Acerola-orion Heart-under-blade
has fully revived.
キスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレード
が完全復活したという話について
Let's hear the details about that.
詳しく聞かせてもらおうか
That is something that directly
relates to my own safety.
それは僕の身の安全に直結する話だ
I had thought she was a young
girl that were some dregs,
絞(しぼ)りかすの幼女だと思っていたから
散々(さんざん)奴に悪態(あくたい)をついてきたけれど
so I've been merciless with the insults.
But, if she is back to her complete self, I
have to alter that attitude drastically.
完全体となったのならば
その態度を豹変(ひょうへん)させなければならない
Big Demo-ther.
鬼いちゃん
Can you teach me how to speak politely?
敬語の使いかた 教えてくれない?
Black Scene
Is Heart-under-blade-sama taking a drink
(kikoshi-mesu) within that shadow?
その影の中に ハートアンダーブレードさまは
聞(きこ)し召(め)すのかな?
You're using the phrase
"kikoshi-mesu" wrong.
聞し召すの使いかた間違ってるよ
I'm guessing that the intended question was
whether or not she was lurking inside the shadow.
No, she's not here.
いや いないよ
Shinobu is with Gaen-san
together with Hachikuji.
忍は 八九寺と一緒に臥煙さんのところだ
A meeting, or rather, a discussion,
about what to do from here on.
これからに向けてのミーティングというか
ディスカッションというか
"What to do from here on"
arouses my interest.
これからに向けて というのは気になるな
After all, Big Demo-ther, you finally were
able to return to being a normal guy.
折角(せっかく)鬼いちゃん
普通の男の子に戻れたっていうのに
What, are you still going to
do something from here on?
何 まだこれから何かするつもりなの?
Even if it is exactly what Gaen-san wants?
それが臥煙さんの手のひらの上だとしても?
Well, concerning that case, I don't
think I gave a clear answer...
いや 別にその件について
はっきり返事をしたつもりはないけれど...
Besides, there's the bit
about Kagenui-san, too.
それに 影縫さんのこともあるしな
Yoduru Kagenui
And—Meme Oshino. Where are they now?
If it's about Big Brother Oshino, isn't he
just leading his usual wandering lifestyle?
忍野のお兄ちゃんに関して言うなら
単にいつも通りの放浪生活をしているだけなんじゃないの?
We've gone this far to search for him, but
he's still nowhere to be found, you know?
これだけ手を尽くして探しても未だ見つからないんだぜ?
Even the Hanekawa is searching,
and can't find him, right?
あの羽川が探して見つからないんだぜ?
Yeah. The girl that doesn't run everything...
No, that doesn't know everything.
It's not like that person is a professional
at finding people or anything.
別にその人だって
人探しのプロってわけでもあるまいに
Well, I have no intent on meddling
in how you think, Big Demo-ther.
まあ 鬼いちゃんの考えかたに口出しするつもりはないよ
By the way, in the case of Big Sister,
ちなみにお姉ちゃんに関しては
僕は武者修行の旅に出たと推理している
I deduce that she went on a trip to
perfect her martial arts skills.
But Ononoki-chan, what will you do if
Kagenui-san is gone like this and never returns?
だけど斧乃木ちゃん もしもこのまま
影縫さんが戻って来なかったらどうするの?
What happens if Kagenui-san
doesn't come to pick you up?
影縫さんが きみを迎えに来なかったら
In that case...
そのときは...
I guess I'd have to be
in this house forever.
この家でずっと過ごすしかないだろうね
Of course, Big Demo-ther, if you
get married and leave this house,
当然ながら
鬼いちゃんが結婚して家を出るようであれば
I'll tag along to wherever you go.
その先についていくけれども
Don't be putting up some
preposterous plan for your life.
とんでもないライフプランを立ててんじゃねえよ
What do you mean, "of course (touzen)"?
何が当然ながらだ
Would it have been better to say
"astonishingly (gakuzen)"?
愕然(がくぜん)ながらのほうがよかったかい?
But still, Big Demo-ther, watching over you is
the task that I am currently assigned to do.
しかし鬼いちゃんの監視が
今の僕に課せられた任務だからね
Until I am relieved of that, I can't
possibly separate myself from you.
それが解除されるまでは
離れるわけにはいかないのさ
In other words...
つまり
お姉ちゃんがこのまま帰って来なければ
If Big Sister is gone like
this and never returns,
Big Demo-ther, you and I will
be in an eternal fellowship.
鬼いちゃんと僕は
一生のお付き合いということになる
Eternal...
一生...
Back to the main story
By the way, Big Demo-ther.
ところで鬼いちゃん
By the way, by the way, Big Demo-ther.
ところでところで鬼いちゃん
How in the world did those
college entrance exams go?
受験のほうは一体全体どうだったのさ?
Well, I did what I could. You did take
care of me, so thank you for that.
まあやるだけのことはやったよ
きみには世話になったね ありがとう
You're welcome.
どういたしまして
Were the results being announced after the
graduation ceremony, or beforehand?
発表は 卒業式のあとなんだっけ
前なんだっけ?
After.
あとだ
Hmm, then it may be a good idea to
have the date sooner than later.
ふむ じゃあデートを早目にしておくというのは
いい案なのかもしれないね
After all, it'd be hard to go out
after one of the two gets rejected.
片方が落ちてからじゃあ
やっぱり行きづらいものね
I would like to think Senjougahara didn't set
the date to be tomorrow from such an intent...
そんな意図で戦場ヶ原は
デートの日程を明日に設定したわけではないと思いたいが
Big Brother!
お兄ちゃんー!
You took one of the plushies from
my room again, didn't you!?
また私の部屋からぬいぐるみ持ってったでしょー!
Oh!
あ あった やっぱり!
Here it is! Just as I thought!
Geez, stop it already. Don't enter
my room without permission!
もう やめてよね 勝手に部屋に這入るの!
You have it lying on your bed and stuff.
ベッドの上に寝かせたりして
You weren't using it for weird things
or anything, were you, Big Brother?
変なことに使ってたんじゃないでしょうね
お兄ちゃん
This is my precious plushie.
私の大切なぬいぐるみを
No, it wouldn't even be exaggerating
if I said I was entertaining it...
いや むしろもてなしていたと言っても
過言ではないのだが
I'm not the type that has a
lot of plushies and stuff.
私って そんなにぬいぐるみとか
持つほうじゃないんだけれど
But for some reason, I feel sympathy
for this particular plushie.
不思議とそのぬいぐるみにはシンパシーを感じてるからね
That's why I've told you again and
again that you can't take it out!
だから持ち出し禁止だって何度も言ってるじゃない
Sympathy, huh?
シンパシーねえ
Big Brother, you were home.
お兄ちゃん 帰ってたんだね
Now that entrance exams are over,
you can play as much as you want!
受験が終わって これからは遊び放題だね!
Big Brother is going to be in
college from next month, huh?
お兄ちゃんも来月からは大学生かー!
That's cause for celebration! I'll
prepare for a celebration!
これはお祝いだね! お祝いの準備を進めるよ!
Tonight, we'll gather all the neighborhood
middle school girls, and have a party!
今晩は 地元の女子中学生を全員集めてパーティだ!
So optimistic...
前向きだな...
Hm... That's not a bad proposal,
ふむ 悪くない提案だが
but unfortunately, I already have
an appointment for tomorrow.
残念ながら明日は先約があってな
But, if it's sometime this month,
I can manage to make some time.
だが 今月中のどこかでというのならば
時間を作ってやってもいいぜ
Oh, Big Brother, you've gained
some composure now.
おー お兄ちゃんも
心の余裕が出てきたじゃない
Until a short while ago,
ちょっと前までは妹から遊びに誘われたら
その場でパンチだったのに
when your little sister invited you to go
play, you just punched her on the spot.
Was I that raging a big brother?
そこまで強烈な兄だったか!?
Then, we'll say sometime this month.
じゃ 今月中どっかでってことで
Yeah. I'll leave you to do the planning.
おう プランニングは任せるぜ
I see, but Big Brother's going on a date
with Senjougahara-san tomorrow, huh.
そうかー でもお兄ちゃん
明日は戦場ヶ原さんとデートかー
I'm jealous that you're so lovey-dovey..
いーなーアツアツで
I've been dating Rousokuzawa-kun for so
long that we've basically settled down.
私なんか 蝋燭沢(ろうそくざわ)くんとは付き合い長くなってきて
落ち着いてきちゃったって言うか
Or rather, he invited me to go
out somewhere for White Day...
ホワイトデーどっか行こうよって誘われたのに
...but for some reason or
another, I declined.
なんとなく断っちゃったもんなー
Wait, huh? Did I tell you that my prior
appointment was with Senjougahara?
って あれ? 先約の相手が戦場ヶ原だって
言ったっけ?
I can tell even if you didn't tell me.
言わなくても大体わかるよ
A prior appointment on March 14th means that
it's with a lover, or with Einstein.
三月十四日に先約となれば
それは恋人かアインシュタインが相手だって
If it was with Einstein, that
would be a huge deal!
アインシュタインが相手だったら大変なことだろ
Well, you're right.
まあ 正解だよ
All right, then tomorrow I'll
go visit Nadeko-chan.
よーし じゃあ私は明日は
撫子ちゃんのお見舞いに行こうっと
She got released from the hospital, but
she's still resting up back at home.
退院はしたけれど
あの子 まだ自宅療養中だからねー
Apparently, she'll start going
to school in the new term.
学校には新学期から行くんだってさ
I'm sure she's lonely if she's
cooped up all alone in the house,
家で一人でこもってたら寂しいだろうから
so I should go over and be really rowdy!
私が行って騒がしくしてあげよう!
You're going there pretty often.
結構... 足しげく通ってるな お前
To be honest, it's unexpected.
正直 意外だけど
Even if you said you were friends,
友達って言っても お前と千石
そこまで仲がいいイメージがなかったから
you and Sengoku didn't give me an image
that you were that good friends.
That's not true. We're
totally best friends!
そんなことないよー
大親友だよー
She told me a secret the other day, too.
こないだ 秘密も教えてもらったしねー
A secret? What's that?
秘密? なんだそりゃ
It's a secret, so of course
I won't tell you.
秘密なんだから言うわけないじゃん
Eh?
Now, now... Leave Nadeko-chan to me,
まあまあ 撫子ちゃんのことは私に任せて
お兄ちゃんは戦場ヶ原さんとラブラブしてくればいいよ!
and Big Brother, you can just go
lovey-dovey with Senjougahara-san!
March 14th
Naoetsu
Judging from the plates,
it's a rental car.
Black Scene
Welcome to a wonderful today.
素敵な今日へようこそ
I tried to be conscious of
the old Hanekawa-san.
昔の羽川さんを意識してみたんだけれど
Your sense of friendship
is a bit too big a burden...
だからお前の友情感 ちょっと重いんだって
Even for you, Araragi-kun,
阿良々木くん的にも
私が羽川さんに寄せていったほうが嬉しいんじゃないかとも思って
doesn't it make you happier if I got myself
closer to what Hanekawa-san is like?
That's another heavy statement there...
その発言も重いな...
Now, let's go. I have to
be back here by 7:00PM.
さて 出発よ
夜七時までにはここに帰ってこないといけないから
I can't be late for my appointment with
Father, so we have to hurry things a bit..
お父さんとの待ち合わせに遅れるわけにはいかないので
気持ち巻いていかないと
We don't have a moment to spare!
ことは一刻を争うわ
Um, can you not have your dinner with
your father tonight be your main event for today?
あの 夜のお父さんとのディナーのほうを
今日のメインに据えないでくれる?
It's okay if it's the main event for you,
据えてもいいけれど 口には出さないで
but please don't bring it to words.
Heh.
Then, why don't you quiet
me down with a kiss?
ならばキスで黙らせて... みなさいよ
Now, go into the passenger seat.
さあ 助手席に乗って
Eh?
Eeh?
Eeeeehh?
Waitgahara-san,
待ってヶ原さん
Wait, wait, wait, wait!
待って待って待って待って
Perhaps it may be, but can it be that
you're driving the car today!?
ひょっとしたらひょっとするかもしれないんだけれど
ひょっとして今日は お前がクルマを運転するってこと!?
You're going to be controlling
the steering wheel?
お前がハンドルを操作するってこと!?
Hitagi Drivergahara!?
ドライバーヶ原ひたぎ!?
Ta-dee-dah!
じゃんじゃじゃーん
Name: Hitagi Senjougahara
Valid Until August 7th
Hehe, were you surprised?
ふふっ 驚いた?
Araragi-kun, while you were feverishly
studying for entrance exams,
阿良々木くんが受験勉強に躍起になっている間
I was also studying hard for the exam
to obtain a driver's license, too.
私は私で 自動車免許取得のために
試験勉強を頑張っていたというわけよ
Got it on the first shot.
一発合格
Y-Y-You know your school rules!?
お お お前 校則って知ってるか!
Not only would acceptance to a college
by recommendation be cancelled,
推薦で決まってる大学の合格が取り消されるどころか
卒業も危うくなるレベルの蛮行である
this level of barbarism will cast
shadows on graduation, too.
In the first place, Senjougahara,
why did you do such a thing?
そもそも戦場ヶ原
お前なんでそんなことをしたの?
I mean, I didn't have to go
to school for the third term,
だって 三学期 学校に行かなくてよかったから
暇で暇でしょうがなかったから...?
so I was bored, so bored,
that I couldn't help it.
An idle brain is the devil's shop.
Besides, see? Araragi-kun, you probably wouldn't
be able to obtain a driver's license,
それに ほら
阿良々木くんが 免許を取得できないだろうから
so I thought I'd get ahead.
先回りしておこうかなと思って
Well, in the end that turned out to be
unnecessary anxiety for me, it seems.
まあ 結果それは余計な気苦労になってしまったようだけれど
Photo Booth
Until yesterday, one symptom of the physical
advancement of my vampiric nature...
僕はつい昨日まで 肉体の吸血鬼化によって
写真に写らないという症状を呈していたのだった
...caused me to not show
up in photographs.
Test #
That means I would not be able to have
a driver's license issued to me...
つまりそれは
運転免許証の発行ができないという意味であり
Name: Koyomi Araragi
And so for that aspect, Senjougahara was
being attentive in her own way, I guess.
その辺に戦場ヶ原は 戦場ヶ原なりに気を回してくれた
ということらしい
When I think about it that way, it was
misconduct that was hard for me to scold her for.
そう思うと 叱りにくい非行だった
Black Scene
No, wait, that just can't be.
って いや そんなわけあるか
Don't think that I'd get
moved by emotions.
情にほだされると思うな
I won't be moved by affection, either.
愛情にだってほだされねえぞ
If you become unable to graduate, that
would mean you had the wrong priorities.
お前が卒業できなくなったら
本末転倒じゃないか
If that happens, I'll break
up with you, Araragi-kun,
そのときは阿良々木くんと別れて
神原と仲良くするから大丈夫よ
and be chummy with Kanbaru,
so I'll be fine.
Don't nonchalantly say that
you'll break up with me.
僕と別れてとか さらっと言うな
And Kanbaru would surely get
slightly bewildered by that,
そして神原だってさすがに面喰(めんくら)うだろ
if she ends up in the same class as you.
お前と同じクラスになったりしたら
I think she'd rejoice
in a carefree manner.
あの子は無邪気に喜びそうだけれどねえ
It seems like I'm the one
that has to compromise.
僕が折れるしかなさそうだ
Araragi-kun, you're the one that needs
to remember to fasten your seatbelt.
阿良々木くん
あなたこそシートベルトを締めるのを忘れないでね
Yeah, I know...
ああ わかってるよ...
I don't have enough courage to ride with someone
who just got their license without a seatbelt.
僕だって
若葉マークのクルマにベルトなしで乗るほどの度胸はないよ
Normally I'm called a raging bull,
but for today, I'm a chicken.
いつもは猛牛と呼ばれる僕も今日ばかりはチキンだよ
BABY ON
BOARD
If possible, I'd even like
to be in a child-seat.
できることならチャイルドシートに乗りたいくらいだぜ
So, where is our destination?
で 目的地はどこなんだ?
The planetarium.
プラネタリウム
Planetarium?
プラネタリウム?
Yes. Planetarium.
そう 天象儀(てんしょうぎ)
Oh, by the way, Araragi-kun.
ああ そう言えば 阿良々木くん
昨夜 羽川さんから電話があったわよ
I received a phone call from
Hanekawa-san last night.
Eh? Really?
え? そうなの?
Yes. It was something about somehow being
able to make it back for graduation.
ええ 卒業式にはなんとか帰れそうだという話だったわ
I see...
ふうん...
It feels like I haven't seen Hanekawa
in quite a long time now.
もうなんだか随分長い間
羽川に会っていない気がするな
What? That means that she called
you, but she didn't call me?
何? これはつまり お前には電話があったけれど
僕のところにはなかったということになるの?
Right.
そうね
I wonder why Hanekawa-san
didn't call Araragi-kun.
どうして羽川さんは阿良々木くんには電話をしなかったのかしら
Perhaps it was because I told her
that I'll tell you for her.
ひょっとしたら私が
阿良々木くんには私から言っておくと言ったからかしら
No other reason can be thought of!
それ以外考えられないだろ
"Tsubasa Hanekawa-sama,
The weather has been warming up lately. How have you been doing?
I have acknowledged your intent to attend the Naoetsu High School Graduation Ceremony on 3/14.
I am very pleased that we will be able to share in the joy of that day together.
(Excised)
Note that I will tell all parties involved, particularly Koyomi Araragi, about this, so no need to worry.
So Please do not contact Koyomi Araragi yourself.
Thank you.
PS: Please do not called Araragi-kun Directly"
Specifically, it might be because I asked
her to not call you, Araragi-kun.
具体的には
阿良々木くんには電話をしないでとお願いしたからかしら
You went that far? You said something that
specific? Why did you do such a thing?
そこまで言ったのか そこまで具体的に言ったのか
なんでそんなことをするんだ
Petition
Oh, that's right. I had been given a message
by Hanekawa-san to convey to you.
ああ... そうそう
羽川さんからの伝言を承(うけたまわ)っていたのだったわ
Convey?
承って?
That's some mysterious polite talk.
She said she found Oshino-san.
忍野さん見つかったんだって
Hmm...
ふうん...
Huh!?
Seriously?
マジで?
Seriously.
マジよ
Well, to be precise, the story was that she
found out where Oshino-san was hiding...
まあ 正確に言うと
忍野さんが潜伏している場所がわかったという話だったかしら
Though, I don't remember it too well.
よく覚えてないけれど
I beg of you, please remember.
Give it everything you got.
頼むから思い出してくれ
全力を尽くしてくれ
Though, she said after many deductions,
ただ 推理を重ねてみると
もう忍野さんの居場所は 二ヵ所に絞られると言っていたわ
Oshino-san's possible whereabouts were
narrowed down to two locations.
Two locations?
二ヵ所...?
Yes. I wasn't interested so I didn't ask about the
details. But that's definitely what she had said.
ええ 興味がなかったから詳しくは訊かなかったのだけれど
確かそう言っていたわ
I wonder what it was.
なんだったかしらね
She said it was the reverse.
逆だったって言ってたわ
Reverse?
逆?
Yes. That her approach was the reverse.
ええ アプローチが逆だった と
Reverse? What does that mean?
逆? どういう意味だろう...
She was making remarks such as
"This is a pen" or something.
ディスイズアペンとかなんとか仰ってらしたけど
Making remarks?
仰ってらしたけどって
"This is a pen"?
ディスイズアペン?
There is much to think about,
and I'm still worried,
but it seems there's nothing I can do in my current state.
What other stuff did you
talk about with Hanekawa?
他にどんな話をしたんだ? 羽川とは
Did she say anything other
than the bit about Oshino?
忍野のこと以外 何か言ってなかったか?
Let's see. I consulted with her
about my plans for today's date.
そうね 今日のデートプランについて相談したわ
I'll confess.
白状してしまうと
Actually, it was Hanekawa-san's
idea that it would be good
実は まずはプラネタリウムに行けばいいというのは
羽川さんの案よ
to first head over to a planetarium.
Is that so?
そうなの?
Personally, a planetarium is a place
where I frequently go to begin with.
個人的にはプラネタリウムって
普段から行くことも多い場所だから
So, for me, it doesn't feel like
much of a special event.
私にとってはイベント性に欠けちゃうのだけれどね
But, it's rather stylish to go
together with you, Araragi-kun.
でも 阿良々木くんと共に行くというのも乙なものだわ
Hmm... But, that said, wouldn't it be a date
that's lacking in amusement for you?
ふむ... でも そうは言っても
お前にとっては面白味のないデートになるんじゃないのか?
Well, when I go to a planetarium,
it's not for leisure,
まあ 私がプラネタリウムに行くときは
遊びに行くというよりも
and the side about learning
something tends to kick in...
お勉強に行くという側面を帯びがちだからね
Once in a while, I'd like to head into seeing
artificial stars without mentally preparing to do so.
たまには気構えずに作り物の星々に臨みたいものよ
It's not a case where I lack enthusiasm,
either. So, rest assured in that aspect as well.
乗り気でないなんてことはないから
そこも安心しておいて
The side about learning
something? Oh, I see.
お勉強に行くという側面?
あ そっか...
You were rather acrobatic for
being a student at our school...
お前確か 理科の選択科目で
地学を選択するという
in selecting geoscience for
your science elective.
我が校の生徒としては
なかなかアクロバティックなことをしていたんだったな
I must say, I don't even know what
people study in the field of geoscience...
For Senjougahara, who cherishes memories of going to
the observatory with her family  when she was young,
it seems that she has special emotions
invested into celestial bodies after all.
I want to know something.
ちょっと知りたいんだけれど
戦場ヶ原 地学ってどういうことを学ぶの?
Senjougahara, what do you
study in geoscience?
It's not like you simply learn all
about celestial bodies, right?
単純に 天体のことばかりを学ぶってわけでもないんだろ?
To be precise, it's an abbreviated
form of "earth sciences".
厳密には地球科学の略よ
Earth Sciences
In other words, we mainly learn about
Earth as a celestial body, I guess.
つまりメインは天体としての地球を学ぶということになるのかしらね
I can't help it that my fascination points
towards the entire universe, though.
私の興味はどうしても
宇宙全体に向いてしまうけれども
Someday, I'd like to draw the perfect space
map, and be dubbed Tadataka Inou the Second.
いつか完全なる宇宙地図を描いて
二代目 伊能(いのう)忠敬(ただたか)と呼ばれるのが 私の夢よ
That's my dream.
Tadataka Inou the Second...
二代目伊能忠敬って...
That is what I want to do in college.
私が大学でやりたいことよ
This is the first I've heard of this.
But my girlfriend is striving
to become an astronaut...
Is that for real?
More like, what's a space
map? Such a thing exists?
って言うか 宇宙地図って何?
そんなのあるの?
Most of space is a vacuum,
and galaxies, groups of stars,
宇宙って ほとんどが真空で
その中にまばらに銀河
are sporadically placed in it.
星々の集まりがあるって配置なのよね
Probability-wise, it seems like stars are
dispersed equally within the vacuum,
なんとなく確率的には
真空に均等に星がばらけてそうに思えるけれど
but in reality nothing like that happens.
実際にはそんなことはなく
The stars clump up, and exist
terribly out of balance.
星々は塊(かたまり)となって
偏って存在しているの
Drawing that into a diagram
is a space map.
それを図に描いたものが宇宙地図
Perhaps stars are like people,
and easily feels loneliness.
星も人間同様
寂しがり屋ってことなのかしらね
You talk like this is a lesson,
教訓っぽいことを言われても
but I've never seen an actual space map, so
it just doesn't click with me at all...
その宇宙地図自体を見たことがないから
まったくぴんと来ないんだけれど
By the way, a space map is not a square like
a map of the world, or a map of Japan.
ちなみに宇宙地図は
世界地図や日本地図のような四角形ではなく
It's in the shape of a hand fan (ougi).
扇の形をしているわ
Ougi...
扇...
To that word, I... don't react.
その言葉に僕は... 反応しない.